Guide to the W.H. Cowley Papers SC0196
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Personal papers and writings, Series 1
  - Correspondence, writings and speeches, 1922-1978; Series 1C
    - Outgoing correspondence: chronological files
      - 1975 (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - 1976 (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - 1977 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - G9.2 SOCIETY: CORRESPONDENCE AND DIRECTORY (Box 18)
  - Papers, 1922-1971; Series 1D
  - Lecture outlines, 1945-1968; Series 1E (Box 1-4)
    Annotated lecture outlines and readings for Cowley's classes at Stanford make up this series. These are bound by course. These materials are very comprehensive; Professor Cowley prepared thoroughly for his classes and organized his subject matter carefully. Included in this series are student reaction sheets. (Cowley handed out lecture outlines early and required his students to read them in advance of class discussion and comment on them in writing.) The 1967 version of his basic course, "A Holistic Overview of American Colleges and Universities," it is closer to a polished manuscript than a collection of lecture outlines. Cowley had planned to publish this volume which concentrates on his taxonomic or conceptual approach to the study of higher education, and it remains one of his two major unpublished manuscripts.
- Research files, Series 2
  - "F" files, 1922-1978; Series 2A
    This series is the first of Cowley's research series comprisises 'professional notes' or 'PN' files and his folder files. Numbers to the left of the decima1 point are coded for a specific subject. Numbers to the right of the decimal point are accession numbers. Thus, the number 220.26 would mean the item is the 26th file on subject 220, the Professorship. This same numbering system is also used in Series II-B, the pamphlet series, and in Series II-C, the workbook series. A list of the subjects corresponding to the numbers is appended at the end of Series II-C.
    These notes, typed on 8" by 5" paper, are significant excerpts or paraphrases taken from books, articles, and papers read by Professor Cowley. 'PN's' are organized by subject; each subject has its own assigned number. The 'f' files are identical conceptually to the 'PN' files, but different from 'PN's' in size. 'F' files are 8 1/2" by 11 and stored in folders. The 'f' files are numbered using the same classification scheme as 'PN's'.
    Included in the 'f' files are numerous papers written by Cowley's graduate students. Cowley considered these very important to his research, while in turn, his meticulous comments on the style and content of these papers benefitted his students enormously.
    Until 1945, Cowley kept three separate indices to the 'PN' and 'f' files by subject, institution and date. After 1945, he maintained one by author only.
    W.H. Cowley's "f"and "PH" files are research materia1s classified by numbers.
    - F1.1- f14.3 (Box 1)
    - F16.1 - F45.25 (Box 2)
    - F45.26 - F83.2 (Box 3)
    - F83.3 - F201.117 (Box 4)
    - F201.118 - F206.20 (Box 5)
    - F206.21 - F206.101 (Box 6)
    - F206.102 - F212.22 (Box 7)
    - F212.23 - F220.25 (Box 8)
    - F220.26 - F235.8 (Box 9)
    - F235.9 - F254.5 (Box 10)
    - F254.6 - F271.1 (Box 11)
    - F273.1 - F306.3 (Box 12)
    - F306.4 - F327.42 (Box 13)
    - F327.43 - F342.10 (Box 14)
    - F342.12 - F391.2 (Box 15)
    - F392.1 - F410.29 (Box 16)
    - F410.30 - F413.1 (Box 17)
    - F413.2 - F414.67 (Box 18)
    - F414.74 - F1022.9 (Box 19)
    - F1023.1 - F1100.4 (Box 20)
    - F1100.5 - F1139.1 (Box 21)
    - Indexes kept by Cowley to PH and F files (Box 22)
  - "PN" files
    - PN1.237- PN13.165 (Box File Cabinet 1)
    - PN20.364 - PN204.301 (Box File Cabinet 2)
    - PN204.302 - PN236.243 (Box File Cabinet 3)
    - PN236.244 - PN342.241 (Box File Cabinet 4)
    - PN342.242 - PN1022.378 (Box File Cabinet 5)
    - PN1023.1 - PN1144.2 (Box File Cabinet 6)
  - PT files, 1813-1975; Series 2B
    The 'PT' files are a collection of approximately 1500 pamphlets. They cover a great variety of higher educational and related topics. More than 100 of them were written in the 19th century and deal primarily with academic government, one of Cowley's abiding research interests. This collection is indexed by author and, where appropriate, by institution. In addition there is a list in accession number order.
  - Workbooks, 1938-1978; Series 2C
    Cowley's 'Workbooks' analyze and index for ready access, the vast store of information in the 'PN', tft and 'PT' series. The workbooks are divided into broad subject areas, with each page in a workbook focusing on a particular subdivision of the major subject. Each page lists relevttnt articles, notes, pamphlets and papers from the various series along with the series name and item number and a short summary of the contents of each item. These workbooks organized Cowley's thinking and research. He claimed that his talent for producing' thoroughly researched and beautifully documented papers and articles on a wide variety of topics was a result of this analytical organization.
    In later years fifteen-ring binders replaced "the more conventional three-ring ones. This made for a more elaborate and easily used workbook, but his basic system remained unchanged.
- Miscellaneous, Series 3
  - BINDERS KEPT BY WHC ABOUT HIS COLLECTION
    - General Index to various parts of WHC Collection (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pamphlet index (Series 2-B, PT files) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - WHC inventory to Series 1-B (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - WHC inventory to Series 1-B (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence about the dispostion of the collection, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dissertations sponsored by WHC, 1945-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - INDEXES TO WHC's PROfESSIONAL NOTES, SERIES 2-A
    - Date file: institutional (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Date file: topical source cards (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Date file: chronological (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - INDEXES TO WHC WRITINGS AND CORRESPONDENCE, SERIES 1-B
    - Name index to 1-B (partial, compiled by WHC) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Index of WHC articles by year, (partial) (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Student comments on WHC collections (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Student comments on WHC collections (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - MISC. RESEARCH NOTES, 1976-78 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - CASSETTE TAPES BY WHC, BIOGRAPHICAL (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Reboxed items
  - Binders -- file number or binder title
    - 30-16 (Box 1)
    - 32-25 (2 v.) (Box 1)
    - 33-28 (Box 1)
    - 36-29 (Box 1)
    - 36-30 (Box 1)
    - 37-35 (Box 1)
    - 38-24 (Box 1)
    - 38-25 (Box 1)
    - 39-12 (Box 1)
    - 39-12A (Box 1)
    - 40-20 (Box 1)
    - 40-43 (Box 1)
    - 41-39 (Box 1)
    - 45-2 (Box 1)
    - 46-13 (Box 2)
    - 51-11 (Box 2)
    - 53-19 (Box 2)
    - 46-13B (Box 2)
    - 76-4 (Box 2)
    - 40-42 (Box 2)
    - 33-28 (Box 2)
    - 38-29 (Box 2)
    - 39-2 (Box 2)
    - 75-18 (Box 3)
    - 61-3 (Box 3)
    - 57-23 (Box 3)
    - Professors, Presidents and Trustees 1964 (Box 3)
    - PPST 1961 (Box 3)
    - Trustees Minutes – Hamilton College 1938-1941 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Evaluation - Hamilton College, Vol. 1, 2, and 3 (Box 4)
    - Trustees Minutes – Hamilton College 1941-1944 (Box 4)
    - Yale Memos (7) (Box 4)
    - Yale Memos (6) (Box 4)
    - Academic Government Vol. 1, 2, 3, and 4 (Box 5)
    - Dunster workbook (5) (Box 5)
    - C. U. Structures (Box 6)
    - Structures (Box 6)
    - PI-18 (Box 6)
    - Social Science and Professions (3) (Box 6)
    - Basics Two (Box 6)
    - Basics One (Box 7)
    - Informal Education (Box 7)
    - Structures 2 – Junior college (Box 7)
    - Structures 1 – University (Box 7)
    - Structures (Box 7)
    - Power Workbook (Box 7)
    - Catchall (Box 7)
    - Basics Three (Box 8)
    - Basics Four (Box 8)
    - Polity, Theology, Liturgy (4) (Box 8)
    - Church-State (5) (Box 8)
    - Democracy and Equality (Box 8)
    - Higher Education History No. 1-6 (Box 9)
    - Higher Education History No. 7-8 (Box 10)
    - Person. Secq 3 (Ecclesiastical Personia workbook) (Box 10)
    - Values-Needs-Wants (Box 10)
    - [Taxonomy ?] (Box 10)
    - 1944 Version + 1957 Outline (Box 10)
    - Intellectual Power and Intelligence (Box 11)
    - Humanism and the Humanities (Box 11)
    - Freedom and Academic Freedom (Box 11)
    - The Great Awakening (Box 11)
    - Knowledge and Skills, Kinds of (Box 11)
    - Man and Manpower (Box 12)
    - Philosophy and Ethics (Morality) (Box 12)
    - Religion – general topics (Box 12)
    - Power MS Workbook (Box 12)
    - Power misc. (Box 12)
    - Government (Box 13)
    - Civil Government (Box 13)
    - Psychology (Box 13)
    - Structure Gen'l Workbook (Box 13)
    - Religious Denominations: Structures and their Functions (Box 13)
    - Science Workbook (Box 14)
    - Social Processes (Box 14)
    - Environment (Box 14)
    - 1946-47 Versions (Box 15)
    - Short History of American Higher Education 1961 (Box 15)
    - 1945 – First and Second Versions (Box 15)
    - TSS of chapter (accordion file) (Box 15)
    - First version duplicates (accordion file) (Box 15)
    - Carnegie Book: 1973 analysis (accordion file) (Box 15)
  - Books
    - Books cited in text [WHC 1.3] (Box 1)
    - Books inscribed by author or gift of author [WHC 1.4] (Box 2)
    - Books inscribed by author or gift of author [WHC 1.4] (Box 3)
    - Books inscribed by donors [WHC 1.5] (Box 3)
    - Books inscribed by donors [WHC 1.5] (Box 4)
    - Books inscribed by donors [WHC 1.5] (Box 5)
    - Books reviewed by WHC [WHC 1.6] (Box 6)
    - Books written by former students [WHC 1.7] (Box 7)
    - WHC Republished [WHC 1.8] (Box 7)
    - WHC Republished [WHC 1.8] (Box 8)
    - Books cited in acknowledgements [WHC 1.9] (Box 8)
    - Harvard University President's Reports, 1825-1876 (Box 9)
    - Harvard University President's Reports, 1877-1896/1897 (Box 10)
    - Harvard University President's Reports, 1897/1898-1911/1912 (Box 11)
    - Harvard University President's Reports, 1912/1913-1924/1925 (Box 12)
    - Harvard University President's Reports, 1925/1926-1942 (Box 13)
    - Harvard University President's Reports, 1941-1955/1956 (Box 14)
    - Harvard University President's Reports, 1956/1957-1965/66 (Box 15)
    - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching. Bulletin No. 1 (1907) – No. 6 (1912) (Box 15)
    - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching. Bulletin No. 7 (1914) – No. 31 (1940) (Box 16)
    - Association of American Universities. Annual Conference Proceedings 1900-1935 (Box 17)
    - Association of American Universities. Annual Conference Proceedings 1936-1961 (Box 18)
    - Harvard University President's Reports 1966/67-1971/72 (Box 18)
    - AGB Reports [Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges] 1964-1973 (Box 19)
    - Corson dissertation supplementary materials (Box 19)
- Additonal materials, Accession ARCH-2002-048
  - An Overview of American Colleges and Universities (1960) and Random Writings (1960) - both photocopies of typescripts (Box 1)